<ugens revision="1">
    <!-- // side-effect: advancing sf offset -->
    <ugen name="DiskIn" reads-buf="true" side-effect="true">
        <rate name="audio"/> <!-- implied="true" -->
        <output variadic="numChannels"/>
        <arg name="numChannels" type="int">
            <doc>
                the amount of channels the file and the buffer will have. This is an Int and hence
                must be pre-determined. Different SynthDefs must be created for different numbers of channels.
            </doc>
        </arg>
        <arg name="buf" type="buf">
            <doc>
                the id of the buffer with the correct number of channels and frames
            </doc>
        </arg>
        <arg name="loop" default="false">
            <doc>
                whether the file should loop when its end is reached
            </doc>
        </arg>
        <doc>
            <text>
                A UGen to stream in a signal from an audio file. Continuously plays a longer audio file
                from disk. This requires a buffer to be preloaded with one buffer size of sound. If loop is
                set to 1, the file will loop.

                '''Note''': The buffer size must be a multiple of (2 * the server's block size). See
                `Buffer#cue` for details.
            </text>
            <see>Buffer#cue</see>
            <see>ugen.VDiskIn</see>
            <see>ugen.PlayBuf</see>
        </doc>
    </ugen>

    <ugen name="DiskOut" writes-buf="true">
        <rate name="audio">
            <arg name="in" rate="ugen"/>
        </rate>
        <arg name="buf" type="buf">
            <doc>
                the buffer used internally by the UGen. this number of frames in the buffer must
                be a power of two (this is currently not checked!). The buffer must have been initialized
                with a `write` command whose `leaveOpen` argument is true. Note that the number of channels of
                the buffer and of the input signal must be the same, otherwise `DiskOut` will fail silently
                (and not write anything to the file).
            </doc>
        </arg>
        <arg name="in" variadic="true">
            <doc>
                the signal to be recorded
            </doc>
        </arg>
        <doc>
            <text>
                A UGen which writes a signal to a sound file on disk. To achieve this efficiently, a buffer is
                needs to be provides which is used to buffer the incoming signal.

                '''Note''': It might be that the buffer size must be a multiple of (2 * the server's block size).
                We haven't currently verified this, but to be safe, you should make sure this property is met.

                The signal output by the UGen represents the number of frames written.
            </text>
            <see>Buffer#write</see>
            <see>ugen.DiskIn</see>
            <see>ugen.RecordBuf</see>
        </doc>
    </ugen>

    <!-- // side-effect: advancing sf offset -->
    <ugen name="VDiskIn" reads-buf="true" side-effect="true">
        <!-- note: argument 'rate' renamed to 'speed' -->
        <rate name="audio"/> <!-- implied="true" -->
        <output variadic="numChannels"/>
        <arg name="numChannels" type="int">
            <doc>
                the amount of channels the file and the buffer will have. This is an Int and hence
                must be pre-determined. Different SynthDefs must be created for different numbers of channels
            </doc>
        </arg>
        <arg name="buf" type="buf">
            <doc>
                the id of the buffer with the correct number of channels and frames
            </doc>
        </arg>
        <arg name="speed" default="1.0">
            <doc>
                controls the speed of playback. The buffer is always streamed at a frequency of
                `SampleRate.ir * speed`, so the buffer's own sample rate is irrelevant. Factors below 4 are
                probably fine, but the higher the value, the more disk activity there is, and the more likelihood
                there will be a problem. The following must be true: `rate &lt; bufFrames / (2 * blockSize)`,
                e.g with typical default values, this will be `32768 / (2 * 64) = 256`.
            </doc>
        </arg>
        <arg name="loop" default="false">
            <doc>
                whether the file should loop when its end is reached
            </doc>
        </arg>
        <arg name="sendID" default="0">
            <doc>
                If a value other than zero is used, the UGen sends an OSC message with this id and the
                file position each time it reloads the buffer: `OSCMessage("/diskin", nodeID, sendID, frame)`
            </doc>
        </arg>
        <doc>
            <text>
                A UGen to stream in a signal from an audio file with variable playback speed.
                Continuously plays a longer audio file
                from disk. This requires a buffer to be preloaded with one buffer size of sound. If loop is
                set to 1, the file will loop.

                '''Note''': The buffer size must be a multiple of (2 * the server's block size). See
                `Buffer#cue` for details.

                If the speed is too high, the UGen will not execute, posting a warning.
            </text>
            <see>Buffer#cue</see>
            <see>ugen.DiskIn</see>
            <see>ugen.DiskOut</see>
            <see>ugen.PlayBuf</see>
        </doc>
    </ugen>
</ugens>